Good morning, happy Father’s Day.
Today’s דף daf is דף יט. Daf Yud Tet. We pick up
at the bottom of יח עמוד ב Yud Chet Amud Bet and
we’re dealing with a series essentially of hypotheticals or questions, conceptual questions
that רבא Rava raises about צרורות Tzerorot and the גמרא Gemara is
sort of invested in not resolving any of them because they’re all
fascinating conceptual questions. One is defining what’s the body of the animal
and its כוח, koach, if something you hit something it rolls down
the hill and then it breaks. The other another question is about...
let’s try to see if we can remember all of them. Is...
oh whether... this was a רב אשי Rav Ashi question... whether סומכוס
Sumchus who doesn’t hold of צרורות, tzerorot, what would he hold if
it’s two degrees removed? For two degrees removed, he’d agree that there’s
that that’s half damages or would he say two degrees removed is
still considered to be like כוחו kocho and pays full damages? This
raises by the way an interesting question about what the רבנן Rabbanan
would say about two degrees removed. Would they say you’re totally פטור?
patur? Would they say a quarter? Right? That sort of didn’t get
explored. Okay. Then came the central question which actually was addressed at
the very beginning of the first פרק perek if people remember, whether...
whether when you pay half damage how much is it like קרן?
keren? Other types of payments of קרן, keren, the classic half damages
of קרן. keren. So one question was would it come from the
body of the animal or from cash? That was the major discussion
yesterday. And then the question that we’re looking at right now is
the question about whether you can warn three times to get it
up to full even though by קרן keren the reason for that
is that the reason you’re paying half is lack of full negligence
and the unexpected nature of it, which is not true here. Here
it’s the indirect nature of it. Nevertheless maybe it follows the pattern
of קרן keren and you would pay full after three times. Okay
so that’s the גמרא Gemara the possibility the גמרא Gemara is dealing
with. So we pick up with that on the bottom of יח
עמוד ב Yud Chet Amud Bet and the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תא שמע דתני, Ta shema detani,
three lines from the bottom, דתני רמי בר יחזקאל, detani Rami bar
Yechezkel, so I try to address this question of יש העדאה לצרורות.
yesh ha'ada letzerorot. If it’s warned three times does it go up
to full? רמי בר יחזקאל Rami bar Yechezkel teaches following ברייתא: braita:
תרנגול שהושיט ראשו לאוויר כלי זכוכית ותקע בו ושיברו. Tarnegol shehoshi rosho
la’avir kli zechuchit vetakavo veshivro. So
a תרנגול, tarnegol, a chicken that sticks its head into the head
of a glass vessel, jar or whatever and you know makes a
sound and because of the sound it breaks it, ושיברו משלם נזק
שלם, veshivro meshalem nezek shalem, you pay full. Okay now that’s interesting
right because the sound, the voice is not the direct body of
the animal. We just saw a second ago how that if an
animal defecates right that is not considered the body, it’s something that
comes from the animal. So here too the sound should be a
כוחו. kocho. So it’s actually the perfect disembodied כוחו. kocho. Okay. ואמר
רב יוסף אמר בי רב Ve'amar Rav Yosef amar bei Rav and
a similar teaching: סוס שצנף וחמור שניחר, sus shetzanf vachamor sheni'ar, I
guess, ושיבר את הכלים, veshiber et hakelim, let’s
say a horse whinnies or a donkey brays, think those are the
right words, anyway and their voice caused vessels to shatter, משלם חצי
נזק, meshalem chatzi nezek, pay half.
So what’s the debate? It sounds like the exact same scenarios of
the voices of animals is it full or half? So the גמרא
Gemara says: מאי לאו כגון דעבד תלתא זימני. Mai lav kegon de'avid
telata zimnei. So how do we explain the idea of full? Maybe
we’re talking that it was done it did it three times. And
top of יט עמוד א, Yud Tet Amud Aleph, והכא במאי פליגי,
vehaka mipalgi, this is the debate. מר סבר יש העדאה Mar savar
yesh hada
that once it’s three times it’s up to full, ומר סבר אין
העדאה umar savar ein hada and the other one says it’s not.
So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, Lo, of course with all these
reads like you’re reading the עיקר ikar debate which is you know
into it, like it’s as if that’s the key issue why is
it absent from the explicit discussion? Anyway. The גמרא Gemara says: לא
בחד זימנא, Lo bechad zimna,
no one time, ובפלוגתא דסומכוס ורבנן קמיפלגי, uvaplugta deSumchus Rabbanan kamipalgi,
it’s just the standard debate of סומכוס Sumchus and the רבנן, Rabbanan,
it’s a classic case of צרורות, tzerorot, nothing fancy or special and
the debate is the one that says full holds like סומכוס Sumchus
that in normal צרורות tzerorot you pay full. So now the גמרא
Gemara says one minute: והא משונה הוא, ve'ha meshuneh hu, why are
you paying full?
Why are you paying full? It’s even according to סומכוס Sumchus it’s
done in an unusual way, right? It’s unusual for an animal to
stick its head in a vessel and to shatter a vessel by
the braying or something.
So even according to סומכוס Sumchus that should be half. גמרא Gemara
says: לא דאיכא ביזרני, Lo de'ika bezrani,
so there are seeds in it. So it’s natural that it would
stick its head to get the seeds and I assume that the
idea and that the sound would be powerful enough to shatter it
I guess if it’s in a very tight container you know that’s
not considered משונה. meshuneh. Or maybe again as somebody was asking me
this yesterday, you know if the act that the animal does is
a natural act, even though the circumstances are such that it’s unlikely
it would have led to that result, it’s still not משונה, meshuneh,
meaning if it’s natural for an animal to stick its head into
the vessel because there’s seeds in the vessel and it’s natural for
an animal to bray or to whinny, then the fact that in
this particular case that led to the shattering of a vessel and
most times the neighing doesn’t lead to the shattering of the vessel,
presumably that’s still not משונה, meshuneh, right? משונה meshuneh is judged by
how natural of an
act.
So
they
would I guess.
So okay, we don't have a resolution to this question of העדאה
בצרורות Ha'ada Bitzroros or not. Another question we do not have a
resolution to. בעי רב אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, we keep on going
back between רבא Rava and רב אשי, Rav Ashi, different types of
questions about these, these interesting theoretical questions. Okay. יש שינוי לצרורות לביאנסק
או אין שינוי לצרורות לביאנסק. Yesh Shinui Letzroros Leveyaneshek O Ein Shinui
Letzroros Leveyaneshek. So if you start with the רבנן Rabbanan that you
pay half for, for צרורות, Tzroros, what if an animal does a
שינוי Shinui that leads to צרורות? Tzroros? Okay, so it does something
in an unusual way and if it would have just done that
with its body, we would have called that קרן Keren and pay
half, and now it does it with a way that causes
the pebbles to scatter. So now you could read the question in
two ways. You could read the question of is there a concept
of צרורות Tzroros of קרן? Keren?
Let's say an animal is כוונתו להזיק Kavanaso Lehazik and it causes
צרורות, Tzroros, right? So an animal is trying to gore another animal,
it misses the animal, but it hits into a wall and that
causes pebbles to scatter and that hurts another animal, right? You could
have asked it that way: is there צרורות Tzroros for an act
of קרן? Keren? But because the גמרא Gemara does not make this
a כוונתו להזיק, Kavanaso Lehazik, it makes it משונה. Meshuneh. And if
you remember, the very fact that we categorize משונה Meshuneh as קרן
Keren is itself a חידוש. Chiddush. Why? Because it's unusual, is that
a type of a קרן? Keren? Why don't you just say it's
an unusual רגל, Regel, it's an unusual שן? Shein? But fundamentally it's
trying to get benefit or it's doing it דרך הילוכה. Derech Hilucha.
So maybe if it were קרן, Keren, maybe it would be obvious
that there's no צרורות Tzroros for קרן Keren if it's fundamentally as
קרן. Keren. But this is paying half and fundamentally it's an act
of רגל, Regel, or it's just a natural act of walking, right?
But it's an unusual way of doing it. But fundamentally it's רגל
Regel where צרורות Tzroros are relevant. So can you now say, well,
it's צרורות Tzroros plus משונה, Meshuneh, it'll all be within רגל, Regel,
it'll pay a quarter? Right? So I think that that seems to
be more what the גמרא Gemara's getting at, that the גמרא Gemara
would say if it was a real act of קרן, Keren, maybe
there's no such thing of
צרורות לביאנסק Tzroros Leveyaneshek anyway.
You don't. But do we combine two halves? A half times a
half is a quarter. Okay. You pay a half because of משונה
Meshuneh and a half of that at a half of what you
normally would pay because of צרורות, Tzroros, or you do it the
other way: you pay a half because of צרורות Tzroros and half
of what you normally would pay because of משונה, Meshuneh, so you
get to a quarter.
Right, I can get you if this is like a קנס, Knas,
then maybe you can, you know, do a קנס Knas on, you
know, it's arbitrary anyway. But if it's ממון, Mamon, like then and
I don't understand.
The principle is you pay half of what you would have paid.
So you would have paid half because it's a, because it's צרורות,
Tzroros, but ah, it's משונה, Meshuneh, so משונה Meshuneh tells you pay
half of what you would have paid. So that's the גמרא Gemara's
question. Okay, but I think again it's interesting because it gets to
the question of how much משונה Meshuneh is seen as a קרן
Keren or משונה Meshuneh is seen as a type of a half
payment within רגל Regel or a half payment within שן, Shein, because
the גמרא Gemara does not raise the possibility of is there צרורות
Tzroros for קרן. Keren. So let's take a look.
Okay. בעי רב אשי: יש שינוי לצרורות לביאנסק או אין שינוי לצרורות
לביאנסק. Ba'ei Rav Ashi: Yesh Shinui Letzroros Leveyaneshek O Ein Shinui Letzroros
Leveyaneshek. So the גמרא Gemara says: תפשוט ליה מרבא. Tipshot Leh Me-Rava.
Why don't we just infer from רבא Rava's question that he already
assumed an answer to רב אשי? Rav Ashi? Why?
דבעי רבא: יש העדאה לצרורות או אין העדאה לצרורות. De-ba'ei Rava: Yesh
Ha'ada Letzroros O Ein Ha'ada Letzroros. Is there העדאה Ha'ada for צרורות
Tzroros or not? So now if רבא Rava is saying is there
העדאה, Ha'ada, now again, if you remember just a second ago we
just left off that discussion, it sounded like the העדאה Ha'ada was
a normal צרורות, Tzroros, that it does it three times, does it
go up to full? But here it sounds, and רש"י ותוספות Rashi
Ve-Tosfos sort of figure out how these two discussions work together, that
the question of יש העדאה לצרורות Yesh Ha'ada Letzroros also includes the
idea that if it was a משונה צרורות, Meshuneh Tzroros, the העדאה
Ha'ada would raise it also to full. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. Okay, if he's asking יש או אין העדאה לצרורות, Yesh
O Ein Ha'ada Letzroros, מכלל דאין שינוי. Mikhlal De-ein Shinui. No,
because if רבא Rava would have held that a שינוי Shinui of
צרורות Tzroros is a quarter, then what would העדאה Ha'ada have done
to it? What would it have done to have done it three
times? It would have brought it up to a half. So the
fact that, now again, why we assume this is what רבא Rava
is saying is what רש"י ותוספות Rashi Ve-Tosfos sort of grapple with,
but the גמרא Gemara assumes that רבא Rava's position is whether it's
a normal צרורות Tzroros or משונה צרורות, Meshuneh Tzroros, העדאה Ha'ada will
bring it up to full. So the גמרא Gemara says from that
question, from that assumption, it seems clear that a משונה צרורות Meshuneh
Tzroros is half for רבא. Rava. Because if רבא Rava's saying a
normal צרורות Tzroros or משונה צרורות, Meshuneh Tzroros, העדאה Ha'ada will bring
it up to full, that means before העדאה Ha'ada we were at
half. And therefore רבא Rava presumably is saying that you do not
say a quarter. So the גמרא Gemara says: דילמא רבא אם תמצא
לומר קאמר. Dilma Rava Im Timtza Lomar Ka-amar. Maybe רבא Rava is
saying like, if we can assume a certain answer to רב אשי
Rav Ashi's question, I have a second-level question. אם תמצא לומר אין
שינוי, Im Timtza Lomar Ein Shinui, if you assume that even when
it does a משונה Meshuneh by צרורות Tzroros it's still going to
be a half, יש העדאה או אין העדאה, Yesh Ha'ada O Ein
Ha'ada, will the העדאה Ha'ada bring it up to full? תיקו, Teiku,
we don't know. So anyway, this complicates רבא Rava because this assumes
that רבא Rava's idea of יש העדאה Yesh Ha'ada applies to a
משונה Meshuneh case of צרורות Tzroros and before this we were assuming
רבא Rava's case applied to a regular case of צרורות, Tzroros, but
the גמרא... Gemara... Once again we have another question of רבא *Rava*
or רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi* that we don't have resolved,
which is if you combine שינוי shinui *shinuy* and צרורות tzroros *tzroros*,
do you go down to a quarter? Okay. Hillel, did you have
a question?
No, I was just I was just reading רש"י Rashi *Rashi* about
the question of העדאה ha'ada'ah *hada'ah* again. It seems like that's just
a big area,
but that's what you were saying.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so בעי רב אשי Rav Ashi, *ba'ei Rav Ashi*.
So now רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi* asks the question again.
We raised this yesterday. כוח כוחו kocho לסומכא ככוחו דמי או לא
*Koach kocha lesumka kachocha dami o lo*? Two degrees removed. Does that
count? Is it like its כוח *koach* and it's full, or not
like its כוח *koach*? מי גמיר הלכה halacha ומוקי לה בכוח כוח
*Mi gamir halacha umoki la bekoach koach*? Does he have a tradition
that you pay half in a certain case of צרורות tzroros *tzroros*?
Just for him he would say, "I'm not prepared to apply that
tradition to a case of כוח *koach*. To me, that's the animal
itself. I'll apply it to two degrees removed." או דילמא O dilma
לא גמיר הלכה Halacha? כלל *O dilma lo gamir halacha klal*? Or
maybe he doesn't have the tradition at all, so even כוח כוח
*koach koach* will pay full. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תיקו
Teiku. *teiku*. We don't know the answer. Again, what's not explored and
is interesting to explore is, let's say you don't have a tradition.
Maybe כוח כוח *koach koach* pays zero, right? How about כוח כוח
כוח כוח כוח *koach koach koach koach koach*? Presumably there we should
agree you pay zero. There's a certain point where it's not considered,
it's considered גרמא *grama* and it's indirect, right? So it's interesting that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be assuming the possibility of full
or a half. You could always raise the possibility of zero. What
would you say for the רבנן Rabanan, *Rabanan* of כוח כוח *koach
koach*? Do you pay a quarter? Do you pay zero? Right? All
those things that are not explored. I don't know. Okay. היתה מבעטת
*haysa meva'etes*. So now we are done with all of these interesting
questions raised by רבא *Rava* and רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi*
around צרורות tzroros *tzroros*. You can tell they really got into it
because it's a fascinating it raises a lot of fascinating conceptual questions
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was like it seems to be much
more interested in the question than in resolving the question. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: היתה מבעטת *haysa meva'etes*. Now
back to the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. או שהיתה צרורות tzroros מנתזין מתחת
רגליה ושיברה את הכלים משלם חצי נזק chatzi nezek. *O shehaysa tzroros
menatzin mitachas ragleiha veshibra et hakelim meshallem chatzi nezek*. It was kicking,
or there were pebbles, you know, coming scattering from under its feet,
so then it pays half. So the I we read the משנה
Mishna. *Mishnah*, it kicked the vessel directly, so then it pays half
because it's קרן Keren? *keren*, because it's kicking. It's like מבעטת *meva'etes*,
like intentionally kicking, not just walking. Or it's צרורות tzroros *tzroros* and
it pays half because of the principle of צרורות tzroros *tzroros* of
רגל Regel *regel*. So in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* was combined a
case of קרן Keren *keren* and a case of צרורות tzroros *tzroros*.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has a particular has a question though how to read the case
of the משנה Mishna? *Mishnah*. איבעיא להו ibaya lehu, *Iba'ya lehu*. היכי
קאמר *Heichi ka'amar*? How do you read this משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*? היתה
מבעטת והזיקה בבעיטה *Haysa meva'etes vehizika biv'itah*? Do you read it the
way we just read it? Scenario one: it was kicking and directly
broke something by kicking it. או *o* scenario number two: צרורות tzroros
כארחיה הוא *tzroros ke'orchai hu*? It's just was צרורות tzroros. *tzroros* in
its normal act of walking. So one case of בעיטה be-itah, *bi'uta*
of קרן Keren *keren* and one case of צרורות tzroros *tzroros* of
רגל Regel, *regel*. Okay. משלם חצי נזק chatzi nezek לרבנן היא *Meshallem
chatzi nezek lerabanan hi*. And it's the rabbis, meaning
the second case of the צרורות tzroros *tzroros* is to rabbis. או
דילמא היתה מבעטת והזיקה בבעיטה *O dilma haysa meva'etes vehizika biv'itah*? That
the case of מבעטת *meva'etes* in the is combined I'm sorry, I'm
sorry, let me read it. או דילמא היתה מבעטת והזיקה בבעיטה *O
dilma haysa meva'etes vehizika biv'itah*? Okay, or or you read it that
no, no, the first scenario is like we said, it was kicking
and directly broke through kicking, that's קרן Keren *keren*. או *o* the
צרורות tzroros *tzroros* case is not
a normal צרורות tzroros *tzroros*, it's a צרורות tzroros *tzroros* from the
kicking. או
צרורות tzroros מחמת בעיטה *o tzroros machmas bi'uta*, or צרורות tzroros *tzroros*
from the kicking, משלם חצי נזק chatzi nezek, *meshallem chatzi nezek*. Now
if it's צרורות tzroros *tzroros* from the kicking, right, basically you've got
the case here. היתה מהלכת *haysa mihaleches*, okay,
what's the case? What's the language? היתה מבעטת *haysa meva'etes*, excuse me.
היתה מבעטת *haysa meva'etes*. מבעטת *meva'etes*. Okay, so that's
קרן Keren *keren*. או שהיתה צרורות tzroros מנתזין
*o shehaysa tzroros menatzin*. Now, so the question here is what's this?
Is it do you read it as two scenarios: either it was
מבעטת *meva'etes*, קרן Keren, *keren*, or a completely different scenario, צרורות tzroros
*tzroros*? Okay, just צרורות tzroros *tzroros* through the normal walking. Or do
you read it it was kicking and broke it directly, or it
was kicking and the צרורות tzroros *tzroros* came through the kicking? Okay,
so that's the question. Do you read this as צרורות Tzroros *tzroros*?
Do you read this as צרורות tzroros דקרן *tzroros de'keren*?
Or do you read this, right, צרורות tzroros *tzroros* of רגל Regel
*regel*, or do you read this as מנתזין *menatzin* because of the
מבעטת *meva'etes*? Okay, and then it's צרורות tzroros *tzroros* of בעיטה *bi'uta*
of קרן Keren *keren*. Okay, so that's the question. What is the
case two of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*? Normal צרורות tseroros? *tzroros* or
צרורות tseroros *tzroros* of the בעיטה *bi'uta*? Now if it's normal צרורות
tseroros. *tzroros*, so we have קרן Keren, *keren* and צרורות tseroros *tzroros*,
both pay half, that's the רבנן Rabanan *Rabanan*. But if it's קרן
Keren. *keren* and צרורות tseroros *tzroros* of קרן Keren *keren*, okay, so
צרורות tseroros *tzroros* of קרן keren *keren* is paying half, okay, why
would that be? It would sound like a normal צרורות tseroros *tzroros*
would pay full, like קרן keren, *keren* always pays half. So if
you're telling me קרן keren *keren* or צרורות tseroros *tzroros* of קרן
keren, *keren* pays half, you're saying צרורות tseroros *tzroros* is not a
special case, right? It's just like a normal קרן keren *keren*. So
that would be... סומכוס. Sumchos. Okay, so או צרורות מה משלם חצי
נזק, o tzroros mah mishalem chatzi nezek, הכי אורחיה hachi orchei normally
משלם נזק שלם mishalem nezek shalem would be full, ומני סומכוס היא
umani Sumchos hi and it would be סומכוס. Sumchos Okay, so is
the צרורות tseroros of part two of the משנה Mishna going on
רגל Regel, or going on קרן? keren. Okay, תא שמע מסיפא, tashma
misefa, let's look at the end of the משנה. Mishna דרסה על
הכלי ושברתו, Darsa al hakli v'shibarto, it trampled on a כלי kli
and broke it, ונפל השבר על כלי אחר ושברו, v'nafal hashever al
kli acher v'shibro, and a shard from that כלי kli hit another
כלי, kli, hit another vessel and broke it. על ראשון משלם נזק
שלם ועל אחרון חצי נזק. Al rishon mishalem nezek shalem v'al acharon
chatzi nezek. On the first one full and the second one half.
So that sounds like a classic רבנן, Rabbanan right? The first one
is direct, the second one is indirect. ואי סומכוס מי איתא חצי
נזק? V'i Sumchos mi itey chatzi nezek? סומכוס Sumchos wouldn't hold half.
וכי תימא ראשון ראשון להתזה ושני שני להתזה V'chi teima rishon rishon
l'ataza v'sheni sheni l'ataza ah, maybe it means it stomped on a
כלי, kli, on the first one it pays, it doesn't mean on
the first כלי. kli. It means on the first כלי kli that
got damaged from the shard. It stomped on a כלי kli and
broke it. Okay, the כלי kli you pay full for that. On
the first one that is broken as a result of that, on
the first one hit by the shards you pay full and on
the second one, two degrees removed, you pay half, so then it
would be
סומכוס Sumchos by case of כח כחו. koach koacho. Everybody with me?
Okay. וכי תימא ראשון ראשון ושני שני להתזה V'chi teima rishon rishon
v'sheni sheni l'ataza ושאני ליה לסומכוס בין כח לכח כחו v'shani lei
l'Sumchos bein koach l'koach koacho and סומכוס Sumchos would make a difference
between כח koach and כח כחו. koach koacho. So you can't say
that because we are committed to not resolving that question. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא דבעי רב אשי, ella debaei Rav Ashi, רב
אשי'ס Rav Ashi's question כח כחו לסומכוס ככח דמי או לא ככח
דמי, koach koacho l'Sumchos k'koach dami o lo k'koach dami, he doesn't
know whether what סומכוס Sumchos, would hold. תיפשוט ליה דלא ככח דמי.
Tipshot lei d'lo k'koach dami. Okay, so it's not ככח. k'koach. Okay,
so the end of the משנה Mishna. says, right, שברו shivro and
then what's the end of what's the end of the משנה? Mishna
דרסה על הכלי
ושברתו ונפל השבר על כלי אחר ונפל השבר על כלי אחר.
Darsa al
hakli v'shibarto v'nafal hashever al kli acher v'nafal hashever al kli
acher.
Okay, then it says ראשון rishon is נזק שלם nezek shalem and
שני sheni is חצי נזק. So the question is, does this if
this means if this is סומכוס, Sumchos צרורות tseroros of ביעוט biyut
is half, but normal צרורות tseroros is full, then ראשון rishon נזק
שלם nezek shalem means the first one hit by the shard, right,
that would be כח. koach. And שני sheni would be the second
one hit by the shard, כח כחו. koach koacho. So that would
be a possible read of the משנה. Mishna It seems a little
not פשט pshat but it's not as bad as some of the
other things the גמרא Gemara was saying. Okay, but then you would
be forced to
resolve the position about סומכוס Sumchos. that we don't want to resolve.
So how so anyway so the גמרא gemara says fine. רב אשי
Rav Ashi obviously can't read the משנה Mishna this way because that
would have resolved his question. He can't read the משנה Mishna סומכוס.
Sumchos So the גמרא gemara, says רב אשי כרבנן מוקי לה. Rav
Ashi k'rabanan moki lei. Fine, you're right. רב אשי, Rav Ashi it's
clear to רב אשי the משנה Mishna is not סומכוס Sumchos. because
then because otherwise this would have resolved his question. Okay, so he
reads it like the רבנן Rabbanan, and this means גופו gufo and
this means כח. koach. We're just like we thought. Okay, so presumably
then this is צרורות tseroros of רגל, regel right? That's what it
would be, קרן keren or צרורות tseroros? of רגל regel pays half.
So but no, we're going to say even רב אשי questions how
to read this משנה. mishna. Okay, ובעיא ליה הכי, u'baei lei hachi,
here's רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's question. הייתה מבעטת והזיקה בביעוטה, Hayta mevaetet
v'hizika b'viyuta, צרורות כאורחיה חצי נזק, tzroros k'orchaya chatzi nezek, right?
So reading the משנה mishna like we assumed, directly kicking or normal
צרורות tseroros half, okay, הא מחמת ביעוטא רביע נזק, ha machmas biyuta
revi'a nezek,
but what if it was צרורות tseroros through ביעוט? biyut? It was
צרורות tseroros through ביעוט. biyut. Ah, that would be a quarter, because
that would be a combination of קרן keren plus צרורות. tseroros So
the thing that I said before, this is not just משונה. meshuna.
ביעוט Biyut seems to actually be a כוונתו להזיק kavanaso l'hazik the
גמרא gemara seems to say. Like intentionally kicking something is like a
כוונתו להזיק. kavanaso l'hazik. So the גמרא gemara here seems to say
that if if צרורות tseroros, משונה meshuna is a quarter, צרורות tzrorot.
of קרן keren is a quarter. So what רב אשי would say
is the way you read the משנה mishna, is, is it קרן
keren or normal צרורות tzrorot? is a half, but צרורות tzrorot of
קרן, keren צרורות tzrorot of ביעוט biyut would be a quarter. כאורחיה
חצי נזק. Ki orchaya chatzi nezek.
I'm sorry... הייתה מבעטת והזיקה בביעוטה הא מחמת ביעוטא רביע נזק hayta
mevaetet v'hizika b'viyuta ha machmas biyuta revi'a nezek ויש שינוי, v'yesh shinui,
and then read this way it would resolve the question of צרורות
tzrorot plus שינוי shinui or צרורות tzrorot plus קרן keren would be
a quarter because the משנה mishna, would only be talking about צרורות
tzrorot, of רגל, regel not צרורות tzrorot of ביעוט. biyut. או דילמא
הייתה מבעטת והזיקה בביעוטה או צרורות מחמת ביעוטא, hayta mevaetet v'hizika b'viyuta
o tzroros machmas biyuta, or
no, maybe the משנה mishna is dealing with צרורות tzrorot of ביעוט
biyut and maybe the משנה mishna? is saying that whether you're dealing
with normal צרורות tzrorot or whether you're dealing with צרורות tzrorot of
קרן, keren you're still going to pay a half. צרורות tsroros always
pays a half even צרורות tsroros of קרן. keren. Okay, חצי נזק
ואין שינוי, chatzi nezek v'ein shinui,
and צרורות tsroros plus a שינוי shinui or צרורות tsroros, plus קרן
keren still remains a half. תיקו. Teiku. So now what the גמרא
gemara. said is the following and I want to read the תוספות.
Tosfos. The גמרא gemara said really the question we've got is... How
do you read או שעשה צרורות מנזין? o she'asah tseroros menatzin? Do
you read that as an independent scenario, a normal case of צרורות?
tsroros Okay, and then it's telling you קרן keren or צרורות tsroros,
is a half, or do you read this as a dependent scenario?
It was kicking, or when it kicked, it made צרורות. tsroros Now,
what, why would צרורות tsroros plus kicking still be a half? There's
two possible ways to say that, or what would the חידוש chiddush
be? Either the חידוש chiddush would be what we just said, that
even though it's צרורות tsroros of קרן, keren it's still a half
and it's not a quarter, or what the גמרא gemara said before,
only צרורות tsroros of קרן keren is a half, צרורות tsroros of
רגל regel, is full and it's like סומכוס. Sumchos. So the גמרא,
gemara whichever the two ways the גמרא gemara has suggested, what combines
them then is a basic just interpretation question of how to read
the משנה. mishna Does the second clause of the משנה mishna of
the צרורות tsroros go on the case of kicking or independent? Now,
how would, what would be the implications of that? Oh, well if
it's independent, then it's a straight משנה, mishna kicking or צרורות tsroros
is a half. But if it's going on the case of kicking,
it would be telling you one of two things: either צרורות tsroros
of קרן, Keren, צרורות tzeroros plus שינוי shinui. is still half, אין
שינוי לצרורות, ein shinui l'tseroros, or the reason צרורות Tzeroros plus קרן
Keren is half is because we're going like סומכוס. Sumchos Okay, but
normal צרורות tzeroros would be full. Now there's a very nice תוספות
Tosafos here that makes a good point, like you know, some of
these points that we associate with
דברי סומכוס, divrei Sumchos, I
don't know, so one of, so we haven't introduced סומכוס Sumchos. in
the משנה, mishna, maybe the סתם משנה stam mishna is סומכוס. Sumchos?
So תוספות Tosafos makes a nice point that you know, we would
sort of nowadays call it academic Talmud, but just to show you
that the ראשונים rishonim were quite aware of things that the גמרא
gemara sometimes does, that you know when there's these sort of these
layers of interpretation in the גמרא. gemara Look at תוספות: Tosafos: רב
אשי קא בתר דמוקי לה באו שעשה צרורות מנזין. Rav Ashi ka
batar demokei lah be'o she'asah tseroros menatzin. The גמרא gemara says like
this, תוספות Tosafos says like this: הוי מצי למימר דאי תמצא לומר
קאמר אי תמצא לומר דכי מסיק משום רבנן או סומכוס, Havi matzi
l'meimar de'ee timtza lomar ka'amar, ee timtza lomar dechi masik mishum Rabbanan
o Sumchos, fine that's not what I'm interested in. Okay, וניראה. v'nir'eh.
Now, going about five lines into תוספות. Tosafos. The
line, the line starts with שינוי. shinui וניראה דבעיא דלעיל לא היתה
אלא אי מתניתין איירי בצרורות כדאורחיה או על ידי שינוי. v'nir'eh d'ba'aya
d'le'eil lo haysah ela ee matnisin ayri b'tseroros k'orcheih o al yedei
shinui. How do you read the משנה mishna by the צרורות? tzeroros
Whether it's talking about a normal צרורות tzeroros or צרורות tzeroros plus
תביעות? tvi'os? Right, that was the whole question that was originally raised
in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. איבעיא להו, Ibaiya lehu... right? The
question was how do you read this משנה? Mishna. Is it צרורות
tzeroros normal or is it צרורות tzeroros plus תביעות? tvi'os? Right? And
it didn't explicate what the implications would be. והשתא הוסיף
מדעתו רבנן היא או סומכוס. vehashtah hosif mido'ato Rabbanan hee o Sumchos.
So the גמרא gemara says, oh, what would be the implications? Oh,
well the implications would be, is the משנה Mishnah. like רבנן or
סומכוס? Sumchos And once that didn't work, ורב אשי מפרש איבעיא להו
יש שינוי לצרורות או אין שינוי לצרורות. v'Rav Ashi mifaresh ibaya lehu
yesh shinui l'tseroros o ein shinui l'tseroros. Okay, so basically what you
have is two layers going on here. There's clearly there was a
basic first question of how do you read the משנה mishna without
explaining what the implications would be. And then the גמרא Gemara develops
the idea that either the implications could be, is the משנה mishna
סומכוס Sumchus, or רבנן, or the implications could be, is the משנה,
mishna you know, יש שינוי לצרורות yesh shinui l'tseroros or אין שינוי
לצרורות? ein shinui l'tseroros? So again, when you read it, it seems
like no, no, no, there is a
מחלוקת, machlokes, רב אשי raises this question, you know, the other thing,
but it's making it clear actually these are just developing the implications
of an initial question that was raised.
Yeah, but I'm still trying to understand the גמרא's Gemara reliance on
סתם משנה stam mishna as not being attributable to anybody. Because I
know that we, you know, we had this in גיטין, Gittin, we
said, 'Oh yeah,' or wherever it was, in נדרים Nedarim I think,
like 'Oh the סתם משנה stam mishna was going like so-and-so,' the
גמרא Gemara said it specifically. Here we're willing to explore, you know,
is it unusual for it really to not be attributable to?
I mean I hear the point, I hear the point. The only
thing I could say is that this whole סוגיא sugya that we've
been doing yesterday and today seems very committed to keeping all the
possibilities up in the air, you know, and it's much more interest
in that than in actually resolving what the exact position of the
משנה mishna, was. And I think the גמרא Gemara like I said,
like I don't know how many הלכה למעשה halacha l'ma'aseh cases they
had about צרורות, tzeroros it seems less urgent to come to an
actual הלכה halakhah? and it seems much more fascinating in terms of
the conceptual questions it raises. So I don't think it's being as
committed to that type of a question.
Yeah, just an observation, in general, beyond the fact, you know, presumably
the categories of the ארבעה אבות נזיקין, arba'ah avos nezikin, they have
some kind of logical or reasonable explanations as to why they have
all these parts, right? And when the גמרא Gemara investigates all these
boundary-testing cases, it doesn't ever refer to 'What's the logic?' Right? It's
just 'How to categorize everything?' It doesn't find as far as it
goes, but like it would be nice to take a step back
and say, 'Yeah, if your animal kicked things, it makes sense that,
you know, you're responsible this way and not that way.'
I mean I totally agree with you. I mean I think some
of the questions you could read as exactly questioning like, you know,
what I sort of like, like what I would call like the
formalist approach as a more sort of like logic approach. Like the
question about יש העדאה לצרורות, yesh ha'ada'ah l'tseroros, right? The גמרא Gemara
never unpacks that, but presumably that's the question. If you go by
the logic of it, there should be אין העדאה, ein ha'ada'ah, because
העדאה is about addressing degrees of negligence and likelihood and so on.
But if you go about the formalist type of an approach, well
חצי נזק works that way. After three times it becomes full, right?
So but I now כח כחו koach kocho is another case where
I don't think it's just a straight formalism question, meaning the גמרא
Gemara starts out well does he have this tradition by כח כחו
koach kocho or not at all? But we could easily say the
question is at what degree does it get more removed and it
begins to be in this more gray area, as סומכוס, Sumchus does
סומכוס basically refuse to see grays or does he see grays just
in different places? Right? But I agree with you that the גמרא
Gemara, never, like the גמרא Gemara is interesting in this regard in
that it tries to answer the questions by bringing texts and is
very committed to not resolve the questions, but it never really unpacks
like what the logic behind why should it be one way or
the other. You know, and some of the times we can sort
of figure it out, but yeah, you're right. It does seem very
like formalist here, category oriented. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעי מיניה רבא בר רב חמא מרבי אמי. Ba'ei minei
Rava bar Rav Chama mei-Rabbi Ami.
So second wide line. Rava bar Rav Chama asked Rabbi Ami, and
some say רב חסדא Rav Chisda or some say רבי חייא בר
אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. היתה מהלכת במקום שאי אפשר לה אלא
אם כן מנתזה. Hayta mehelechet bimkom she-ee efshar lah ela im kein
menatza.
It was a place that it was, you know, it was so
filled with pebbles that even any animal that would have walked in
this place would have caused pebbles to scatter. Okay, big deal. It
doesn't matter. It's still צרורות. Tzroros. It's not because whether it could
or couldn't have avoided them and it's חצר הניזק chatzer ha-nizak anyway.
It shouldn't be in this other guy's רשות. reshut. Okay, but the
point being that it was going to happen that that was happening
anyway. ובעטה והתיזה והזיקה. U-be-atah ve-hitiza ve-hizika. And it kicked it and
caused the pebbles to scatter. Okay. So,
מהו? mahu? Is that going to be now שינוי shinui plus צרורות?
Tzroros Because he's basically saying the שינוי shinui is incidental to the
fact that the צרורות Tzroros went and scattered. Not because you could
make a case where it's not incidental. If it was normal walking
it would have only hit ten feet. Because it was kicked it
went twenty feet. But where... but let's assume it's completely incidental. Whether
it would have walked normally or kicked, the pebble would have scattered.
But in this particular instance the pebble scattered because it was kicked.
Is that a case of שינוי shinui, plus צרורות Tzroros, and you
pay a quarter? Or is that just a case of צרורות Tzroros,
because it would have happened even without being kicked? Okay. ובעטה והתיזה
והזיקה מהו? U-be-atah ve-hitiza ve-hizika mahu? כיון דאי אפשר לה אורחיה הוא.
Keivan d'ee efshar lah orchai hu.
Since it was going to happen anyway, we just say it's אורחא
orcha and it's a regular רגל regel and צרורות tzroroth. are רגל
regel. and you pay half. או דלמא השתא מיהא מכח בעיטה קא
מנתזה. O dilma hashta miha mi-koach be-itah ka-menatza. In this particular instance
this pebble was, you know,
was dislodged through an act of בעיטה, through an act of שינוי,
shinui and קא מנתזה. ka-menatza. And that's why it got kicked. תיקו.
teiku. So we don't know. So that's right, that is an interesting
question. The particular act was an act of שינוי shinui, but it
would have happened even had it not been an act of שינוי,
so how do you categorize the nature of the act? Right?
So then if it's חצר הניזק chatzer ha-nizak do you still say
that
it
would be half and not נזק שלם? nezek shalem? What? Because it's
חצר הניזק? chatzer ha-nizak?
Yeah.
That's because it's צרורות, tzroroth. it's רגל, regel right? So I mean
it's an interesting question about what would you say about צרורות tzeroros.
of קרן. Keren. Would צרורות tzeroros, of קרן Keren. pay in רשות
הרבים? reshut ha-rabim? Okay, we haven't really like that's another interesting question
which we haven't directly addressed. Okay, בעי מיניה רבי ירמיה מרבי זירא.
Ba'ei minei Rabbi Yirmiyah mei-Rabbi Zeira. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah asked רבי
זירא. Rabbi Zeira. היתה מהלכת ברשות הרבים. Hayta mehelechet be-reshut ha-rabim. Okay,
now we are going to do it in רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim.
Now again, there's a very interesting question here exactly that issue of
whether you have the word ובעטה. u-be-atah. Because ובעטה u-be-atah makes it
into a type of a קרן Keren and then it raises a
question we haven't addressed yet, which is is צרורות of קרן Keren
חייב chayav in רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim like קרן Keren. and חייב
chayav in רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim or like a רגל regel and
פטור patur in רשות הרבים? reshut ha-rabim? But we're going to take
out the word ובעטה u-be-atah for simplicity's sake. Okay, we can go
back and think about it later. But let's first work without it.
It was going in רשות הרבים והתיזה והזיקה מהו? be-reshut ha-rabim ve-hitiza
ve-hizika mahu? לקרן מדמינן ליה וחייבת או דלמא תולדה דרגל היא ופטורה?
Le-keren midaminan leh ve-chayevet o dilma toldah de-regel hi u-fetura? So without
taking... with taking out the word ובעטה, u-be-atah, it's asking a question
which seems to me, I don't know, to be the first question
I would ask before I would ask the question of מגופו משלם.
mi-gufo m'shalem. This thing is paying half. Okay, so from a payment
perspective the גמרא Gemara said wait a minute, half payment we know
from קרן Keren, is מגופו, mi-gufo, so maybe this should also be
מגופו. mi-gufo. On the other hand, it's רגל. regel But to me,
I don't know, somehow I'm always more interested in the whether you
have to pay as opposed to how you pay. Okay. So I
know. So I'm saying so this asks that question. It says, do
we say half is like קרן Keren. and קרן Keren. pays in
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim and this will also pay in רשות הרבים?
reshut ha-rabim? Or do we say nope, at the end of the
day this is an act of רגל regel. and an act of
רגל regel. pays only in חצר הניזק? chatzer ha-nizak? You might remember
from the very beginning of the סוגיא. sugya. Remember the first סוגיא
sugya in the מסכת masechet where the תולדותיהם כיוצא בהן toldoteihen k'yotzei
bahen or לא כיוצא בהן lo k'yotzei bahen and we said we're
talking about צרורות and that was לא כיוצא בהן, lo k'yotzei bahen,
right? You might remember that because that pays half. And then the
גמרא Gemara says ah but it's still רגל regel? because it's מן
העליה. min ha-aliyah. And then the גמרא Gemara, says wait a minute,
maybe it's מגופו. mi-gufo. That was the unresolved question we had yesterday.
Fine says the גמרא, Gemara. even if it's מגופו, mi-gufo, so the
payment is fully
like
קרן. Keren או דילמא תולדה דרגל הוא. O dilma tolda d'regel hu.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, מסתברא תולדה דרגל הוא. Mistavra tolda d'regel hu.
Finally you have an answer that is resolved not by a text,
but by like, oh logic, it's a תולדה tolda of רגל. regel.
Of course, I find that interestingly without explaining what the logic is
behind it, but of course, I do agree, that is the intuitive
logic. Just because it's paying half doesn't stop it from fundamentally being
רגל. regel, Okay. Now by the way, what is interesting is if
you do have the גרסא girsa of ובעטה, ubyata, right? Then it
is even going further and saying this is the question I raised
before, when the גמרא Gemara had צרורות of משונה, meshuneh, was it
thinking about that as צרורות of קרן Keren or צרורות of רגל?
regel. Right? Maybe the גמרא's Gemara, thinking that even if it doesn't
act of ובעטה, be'ita, all cases of צרורות, even צרורות of קרן
Keren are a type of a רגל. regel. Okay. רש"י Rashi by
the way asks about that in an earlier, I didn't discuss that
yesterday, but remember the גמרא Gemara yesterday about the animal like defecating
and the גמרא Gemara treated that as צרורות, and רש"י Rashi said,
well wait one minute, that's not רגל, regel that's שן, shen, because
it's getting הנאה hana'ah when it's just relieving itself. Okay, so רש"י
Rashi says, well maybe like all צרורות are always defined as רגל.
regel, And I assume what רש"י Rashi means is is that
anything that's indirect, that's not the body of the animal, the animal
isn't getting pleasure, the animal gets pleasure from relieving itself, so the
act of relieving itself is שן. shen. Okay. But the act of
damage where the, where the צרור tsror hit the dough or whatever,
that is not הנאה. hana'ah. The animal doesn't get הנאה hana'ah from
the act of damage. Normal שן shen is the הנאה hana'ah is
derived from the act of damage. So anything that would be a
צרורות of שן, shen, an animal is chomping away at a fruit
and a piece of fruit goes and it hits somebody in the
eye or something like that. Okay, so
the צרורות is completely a type of a רגל. regel. It's an
incidental thing, that's what רגל regel is. By its very nature, צרורות
even originating in an act of שן, shen, you could say the
reality of צרורות is always a type of a רגל, regel. an
incidental damage. Okay. So the same thing could be said here, even
if an animal does a ובעטה, be'ita, unless the animal is consciously
trying to kick the rock to hit somebody in the eye, then
that you could say that that would be כוונתו להזיק. kavanato lehazik.
But if the animal does a ובעטה be'ita trying to do a
כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik right here, and then incidentally the rock goes
off, you could say by definition that's always going to be רגל.
Regel, So that's an even more interesting way of reading the גמרא,
Gemara. that maybe צרורות of קרן Keren. is still fundamentally רגל Regel,
and would still be פטור patur in רשות הרבים. rishus harabim. Okay.
So two ways of reading the גמרא. Gemara And he says מסתברא
תולדה דרגל הוא, mistavra tolda d'regel hu, it makes sense that either
normal צרורות and maybe even צרורות of קרן Keren is still defined
as רגל. Regel. Okay, השתא, haistana, here you have another question. התיזה
ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות היחיד. Hatiza b'rishus harabim v'hezika b'rishus hayachid. This
is a really interesting question again. The גמרא's Gemara going to not
unpack it, but if we think about it, it's really interesting. It's
walking in רשות הרבים rishus harabim and it kicks, and the pebbles
hit my vessel in my רשות היחיד. rishus hayachid. You're taking your
animal where you're allowed to take it, in רשות הרבים, rishus harabim,
and it dislodged a rock that now broke a beautiful vase in
my yard. והזיקה ברשות היחיד, V'hezika b'rishus hayachid, מהו? mahu? So are
you חייב chayav or not? אמר ליה, Amar lei, עקירה אין כאן,
הנחה יש כאן. Akira ein kan, hanacha yesh kan.
If there's no problem in the uprooting, how can there be a
problem in the landing? Which basically means, the way I would, well,
a, it means you're פטור. patur. If the animal was no problem
in רשות הרבים, rishus harabim, how could you be חייב chayav when
it lands in רשות היחיד? rishus hayachid? But the logic makes an
enormous amount of sense, because I think the reason we assume, why
do you assume you're פטור patur in רשות הרבים? rishus harabim? I've
got a right to be here! And as I've got a right
to have my animal here, then as long as I'm not doing
anything unusual, if it's going and goring, or it's doing a משונה,
meshuneh, whatever, fine. But as long as it's just doing the normal
things animals do, and I've got a right to be, you can't
make me responsible for those types of damage. Well, that's true as
well. I've got a right to be here, and it happens to
kick a pebble. I can't be held responsible whether the pebble hits
your vase in רשות הרבים rishus harabim or whether it hits your
vase in your רשות. rishus. עקירה אין כאן, הנחה יש כאן. Akira
ein kan, hanacha yesh kan. If it did nothing wrong by kicking
it, or nothing unusual, then how am I חייב chayav depending on
where it lands? Okay. But the alternative is equally possible, and this
gets to the question here, so though it's not in the גמרא,
Gemara but this is what I'm reading into the גמרא Gemara is
the logic. It gets to the question of why you're פטור patur
in רשות הרבים. rishus harabim. Because the other argument why you're פטור
patur in רשות הרבים rishus harabim is not because I have a
right to be here. It's because you, having your fruit in רשות
הרבים rishus harabim or your vase where you know animals walk around,
that's your responsibility to keep your eye on it. And if you're
not, then you have contributory negligence. Ah, so this is a perfect
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Because I was keeping my vessel in my
רשות. rishus. I wasn't bringing it to רשות הרבים. rishus harabim. And
I have a right. So when I if I go into a
public domain, I've got to be on the watch to make sure
that
I'm protecting it, some other things that could damage it. But I...
I have a right within my רשות Reshus to assume that I'm
going to be protected. Okay, now you could say no, if your
רשות Reshus is near רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim you got to know
that there are flying pebbles, but it's still a little different. Once
fundamentally I'm on in my רשות, Reshus, I am not responsible for
watching to protect my things. You know, you have to stop your
stuff from coming and damaging my stuff. So this seems to get
at the core of why you're פטור patur in רשות הרבים. Reshus
Harabbim. If it's because I have a right to be here, then
if I have a right to be here and the pebbles go
into your domain, I'm פטור. patur. If it's because you're to blame,
then when they go into your domain, you're not to blame and
therefore I would be and therefore I would be חייב. chayav. What
do you want to say?
רשות Reshus is just like an artificial boundary.
It's just a concept, right?
What do you mean it's a concept? It's my property.
But it's weird.
This is my property, then there's the sidewalk and then there's the
street.
The pebble doesn't know, oh now I'm in...
The pebble doesn't know. But there's a legal question, right? So if
the legal question is, did you have a right to be there,
then the answer is yes and you're פטור. patur. If the legal
question is, did I have contributory negligence? The answer is no. I
have no responsibility to watch my vessels that are in my domain
from being damaged by other people. That's not my responsibility. When I
bring them into רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, I've got that responsibility, not
when they're in my domain. It seems like it's a great question
that gets to the core of why you're פטור patur in רשות
הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the
first answer is you're פטור. patur. אכתי איכא הניא אחריא דתניא אשכחן
Acheti eika hanei achraya d'tanya ashkan says the
גמרא. Gemara חיה מהלכת בדרך והתיזה בין ברשות היחיד בין ברשות הרבים,
Haya mehalechet baderech vehitiza bein bireshus hayachid bein bireshus harabbim, an animal
is going and it caused damage whether in the private or the
public domain. חייב, Chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Now this is shocking because
מאי לאו, mai lav, so this seems to answer one of the
two questions we just asked, because here you are חייב chayav in
רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. מאי לאו התיזה ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות הרבים?
Mai lav hitiza bireshus harabbim vehizika bireshus harabbim?
The simple read of this is that it did the kicking and
the damage occurred in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So you see that
צרורות are חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. No, no, no,
no. It means התיזה ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות היחיד. Hitiza bireshus harabbim
vehizika bireshus hayachid. When it says you're חייב chayav in רשות הרבים,
Reshus Harabbim, it means it kicked the pebble
in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim but the damage still occurred in רשות
היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. That's why you're חייב. chayav. צרורות is only חייב
chayav in רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid.
But it says בין ברשות היחיד בין
ברשות הרבים.
bein bireshus hayachid
bein bireshus harabbim. It means whether the kicking, no, means whether
the
kicking occurred in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim or רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid,
but the damage had to occur in רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. Okay,
I understand it's not פשט pshat of the ברייתא. Braisa. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, but at least you have to concede
your second point. ואמרת עקירה אין כאן הנחה יש כאן. V'amarta akira
ein kan hanacha yesh kan. But you said if the act of
kicking wasn't a problem, it's not a problem where it lands. אמר
ליה הדר בי. Amar lei hadar bi. Fine, that I retract. You're
right, because there's evidence that צרורות is חייב chayav in רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabbim. A lot of ברייתות Braisos are going to say that
צרורות is חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So you have
to concede one of the two points: either fundamentally it's חייב chayav
in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, which is really interesting, which makes it
fully like קרן, keren or minimally it's חייב chayav when it's the
kicking in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim and the pebble landed in רשות
היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to continue
with this.
Okay, איתיבי דרסה על כלי ושיברו ונפל השבר על כלי אחר ושיברו
על הראשון משלם נזק שלם ועל האחרון משלם חצי נזק. Eisivei darsah
al kli v'shibro venafal hashver al kli acher v'shibro al harishon m'shalem
nezek shalem v'al ha'acharon m'shalem chatzi nezek. So that's our משנה. mishna
The first one full, the second one half when the shard went
and broke it. ותני עלה במה דברים אמורים ברשות הניזק. V'tanya ala
bameh devarim amurim bireshus hanizak. When is that true? If it's in
רשות הניזק. Reshus Hanizak. אבל ברשות הרבים על הראשון פטורה ועל האחרון
חייבת. Aval bireshus harabbim al harishon petura v'al ha'acharon chayaves. Listen to
the irony. The first one you're exempt because it's רגל, Regel but
then the shard went and broke another one, that you're going to
be חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. So again the simple
reader of this ברייתא Braisa is even normal צרורות are like קרן
keren and חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. And then you
have this irony that you're פטור patur on the one it broke
directly and חייב chayav half on the one it broke indirectly. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו התיזה ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות הרבים?
mai lav hitiza bireshus harabbim vehizika bireshus harabbim? It sounds like a
straight case of צרורות in
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim is חייב. chayav. No, no, no. I'll say
the same thing I said before. התיזה ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות היחיד.
Hitiza bireshus harabbim vehizika bireshus hayachid. When it says חייב chayav in
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, it means that the act was in רשות
הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, but the damage was in רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid.
Okay, so it says like this, ואמרת עקירה אין כאן הנחה יש
כאן, v'amarta akira ein kan hanacha yesh kan, but you said in
that case you're also פטור. patur. אמר ליה הדר בי. Amar lei
hadar bi. Okay, that I have to concede, that I retract. Because
again there's a lot of תנאי Tannaic evidence that צרורות is חייב
chayav in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, which again פשט pshat is that
it's like קרן. keren, But at least minimally we have to concede
that what it means is the kicking happened in רשות הרבים, Reshus
Harabbim, then the damage happened in רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, that at
least you're going to be חייב chayav for. איני, Eini, is this
really true? והאמר רבי יוחנן אין חצי נזק חלוק לא לרשות היחיד
ולא לרשות הרבים. V'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan ein chatzi nezek chaluk lo l'reshus
hayachid v'lo l'reshus harabbim. Doesn't Rabbi Yochanan say when you pay חצי
נזק, it's going to be the same whether in the private or
the public domain? And we assume why did you have to say
a statement like this? Presumably it's a way of saying that צרורות
pays even in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. מאי לאו התיזה ברשות הרבים
והזיקה ברשות הרבים? Mai lav hitiza bireshus harabbim vehizika bireshus harabbim? Isn't
he trying to tell you that צרורות pays in רשות הרבים? Reshus
Harabbim? No, התיזה ברשות הרבים והזיקה ברשות היחיד. Hitiza bireshus harabbim vehizika
bireshus hayachid. No, no, no, again. He means that if it does
the kicking in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim as long as the damage...
damages in רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid you're going to pay half. ואמרת
עקירה אין כאן הנחה יש? Ve'ahmrata akira ein kan hanacha yesh? And
didn't you say in that case you're also פטור? patur? הדר בי,
Hadrei bi, I retracted. Okay, I've seen a lot of that going
on here. כי אמר רבי יוחנן אקרן. Ki amar Rabi Yochanan akaren.
Or maybe Rabbi Yochanan wasn't even talking about צרורות. Rabbi Yochanan meant
קרן. keren You pay half in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim and רשות
היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. He's rejecting Rabbi Tarfon maybe that says קרן keren
you pay full in רשות הניזק, Reshus Hanizak, or maybe he's
rejecting another person's position that says קרן is פטור patur in רשות
הרבים. Reshus Harabim. But maybe he's just talking about קרן. Okay, anyway,
again, the ברייתות Braissos are clear that you pay for צרורות in
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, which really sounds like it's like classic קרן,
even though conceptually it's רגל, Regel the הלכות Halachos are classic קרן.
The גמרא Gemara gets out of it by saying maybe we're talking
about that it's walking in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim but the damage
occurs in רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. Even that though, makes a very
important statement I would say, less about צרורות and more about the
nature of רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, right? And it would basically say
that even though you have a right to be here, since the
guy was keeping his vessels in his own domain, you remain חייב.
chayav. And that is I think the core question of the nature
of רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Okay, and we're actually going to transition
to a similar discussion right now about רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Let's
take a look. איבעיא להו... and we just... okay, יתיב רב יהודה
נשיאה, Yasiv Rav Yehuda Nesia, Rav Yehuda Nesia was sitting, ורבי אושעיא
אקילעא דרבי יהודה, veRabi Oshaya akila deRabi Yehuda, on his like doorstep,
on his like porch. ונפק מילתא בינייהו, Vinafak milta beineihu, and they
raised the following question: כשכשה בזנבה מהו? Kishkisha biznava mahu?
If an animal was like waving its tail and broke something, so
we're not dealing with צרורות, we're back to רגל. Regel. Okay, and
that's the name of the פרק, Perek, כיצד הרגל, Keitzad Haregel, right?
So we've been so hyper-focused on צרורות, there's also just straight רגל
Regel. to talk about. Okay, so an animal is waving its tail
and it broke something. Okay, well we'll see in a minute, what's
the הלכה? Is that רגל regel or not? I mean why not?
Of course it would be רגל. regel, אמר ליה אידך וכי יאחזנה
בזנבה וילך? Amar lei idach vichi yochezena biznava veyeilech? I don't understand,
are you supposed to hold onto its tail as you're walking? Okay,
meaning that... now what does that say? That means that... sounds to
be like the question is that you don't have a right to
be in רשות הניזק, Reshus Hanizak, so it's right, so yeah, hold
onto its tail if you're bringing your animal in my domain you're
not allowed to. So it sounds like the question is רשות הרבים,
Reshus Harabim, okay, are you חייב chayav in רשות הרבים? Reshus Harabim?
And the answer is of course you're פטור patur in רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabim. What are you supposed to do, tie up, you know,
hold your animal's tail while you're walking with it? So what the
point then would be is that this is getting to the
argument of why you're פטור patur in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Why
are you פטור patur in רשות הרבים? Reshus Harabim? What do you
want me to do? I've got a right to bring my animal
here. Am I supposed to like watch every step it takes, tie
up its tail? Like I have to have a certain freedom of
movement, and that gets to the argument of why you're פטור patur
in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Okay, the question still is why was
it asking particularly the question of the tail? Ask it about... that's
classic רגל. regel
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי אפילו קרן נמי נימא וכי
יאחזנה בקרן וילך? Ei hachi afilu keren nami neima vichi yochezena bekaren
veyeilech? All right, so be פטור patur in קרן. Am I supposed
to hold onto its horns while I'm walking it in רשות הרבים?
Reshus Harabim? הכי השתא, Heichi hashta, what type of question is that?
קרן לאו אורחיה, Keren lav orchaya, that's not something to be expected.
הא אורחיה, Ha orchaya, this is to be expected. Now, one minute.
Normally, when we say קרן לאו אורחיה, Keren lav orchaya, that's a
reason for קרן to be more חייב chayav or more פטור? patur?
פטור. Patur. More פטור. patur. But here we're saying the opposite. It's
a reason to be more חייב, chayav, right? Because קרן is חייב
chayav in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim and שן ורגל Shen varegel is
פטור. patur. Isn't that ironic? קרן is not normal, and that's... but
here for רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, yes, that exactly is the difference.
Because it is a natural thing for the animal to do, and
because you have a right to use רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, we
have to exempt you, right? Because we have to say we cannot
obligate you for the normal movement of an animal, then you might
as well not use רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So the fact that
it's natural, although normally that's a reason to be חייב chayav because
it means more negligence, in the case of רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim,
it's a reason to be פטור patur because for society to run,
we cannot make you liable in a public domain where you're allowed
to bring your animal for the natural things that animal... we can
make you liable for קרן. That's not going to stop my freedom
of movement. If I know that I'm going to be חייב chayav
if my animal breaks out into a rage and gores something in
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, it's not going to make me hesitate for
a second to bring my animal in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim because
I'm not going to expect it to do that. But if you
tell me I'm going to be חייב chayav for things it's going
to walk on in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, I'm going to never
bring my animal there, and that's not tolerable. So this is such
a great גמרא Gemara that it basically, I mean it doesn't fully
spell it out, but it's pretty on the surface, right? That it
gets to the פטור ptur for רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim is we
have to give you that freedom of movement, and that's why you're
חייב chayav for קרן and you're פטור patur for שן ורגל, Shen
varegel, ironically the reverse of what we would normally say. But now
we have to say, so why am I asking the question about
the tail? Why is this a special case? גמרא Gemara says, וכיון
דאורחיה מאי קמיבעיא ליה? Vecheivan de'orchaya mai kamibaiya lei? So if the
wagging of the tail is a normal thing, what's your question? So
the גמרא Gemara says, כשכשה יתירה קמיבעיא ליה. Kishkisha yasira kamibaiya lei.
Yeah, let's say it was wagging a little extra vigorously, okay? So
then it becomes a question of משונה. meshuna. Now again here's something
very interesting. Here's something very interesting, right? משונה Meshuna until now we've
been saying is a reason to be more exempt, to pay half.
But what is the case of, we raised this before, of משונה
meshuna in רשות... Reshus... רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. A משונה רגל meshuneh
regel in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Is it going to pay, is
it going to be like קרן and is it going to pay,
or is it going to be like רגל regel and be פטור?
pattur? And this גמרא makes it sound like you would pay. Why
would you pay? You could say like what Dov was saying before.
Well, just formally, we categorize משונה meshuneh as קרן and therefore you
pay in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. But also the logic of רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim should make you pay. The reason you're exempt is
because we have to make you exempt from natural things an animal
is going to do or else you'll never take your animal to
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. But unusual things we can make you liable
and that's still not going to make you hesitate to bring your
animal because you're not going to expect it to happen. So if
this idea of wagging its tail like crazy was משונה, meshuneh, okay,
we might be able to say, you know what, you're going to
have to pay in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. And that's not going
to impact your freedom of movement because it's so unusual that it's
not going to make you hesitate. Okay? It's still a matter of
you having a right. I mean you have a right, don't have
a right to have your animal gore things, but you do have
a right to have your animal wag its tail. How am I
supposed to know that right now it's going to wag it a
little bit vigorously? Right? In that sense I'm not to blame whereas
קרן, you know, I'm... Right, so that's true but so but on
the other hand you're פטור pattur also on שן shen in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. You could say רגל, regel, it's not just to
not constrict my freedom, it's that fundamentally telling me I can use
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim is telling me I can walk there. But
שן shen is different. Telling me I can use רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim is not telling me I can eat things there, certainly not
things that don't belong to me, okay, that my animal can eat
them. So nevertheless the פטור pattur of שן shen and רגל in
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim is not because fundamentally you have a right
to walk and a right to eat. You don't have a right
to eat other people's objects. Okay? It's because at this logic it's
because we think this is a natural thing an animal will do.
We have to... we can't tell you you'd be חייב chayav or
then it would just completely constrict your movement. But still, wagging your
tail is natural. Wagging its tail over-vigorously still consistent with something natural.
Right, so you're right, so what you're saying is that even כשכשה
יתירה kishkeshah yeseirah is still like even a
משונה, meshuneh, if it's a משונה meshuneh of an outgrowth of a
normal type of thing we would have to sort of categorize it
the same way. Right, I hear that. Yeah.
It just seems a little backwards because the very same idea that
it's unusual should also exempt you.
But that's the point, but if here's like a policy override, right,
that's the different way of thinking of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. It's
not a negligence... it's a policy override type of a question, so
we only have to do it for the more common. But yes,
I agree
with Michael, there's a big difference between saying uncommon because fundamentally like
that's like סתם שור בחזקת שימור. stam shor bechezkas shimur. Animals don't
go ahead and gore. Right, it's a complete type of an act
that I never expect. As opposed to this thing, my dog decided
to do some funny way of eating rather than a normal way
of eating, right, or some crazy wagging instead of a normal wagging.
Anyway, but that does raise this question, right? When we say משונה
meshuneh is pays half, how much are we putting it in a
קרן category and because of that you're חייב chayav in רשות הרבים?
reshus harabbim? Or how much are we still keeping it in a
רגל category and then we could
raise questions of רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? Maybe it's not at all
in the
category because there's no צד השוה? tzad hashaveh? Yes, so that went
back when we first raised the משונה, meshuneh, you know, way earlier,
that I pointed out that the גמרא is not clear that משונה
meshuneh is חייב chayav in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, although most ראשונים
Rishonim assume that it is. But you could say that משונה רגל
meshuneh regel is still a type of a רגל, right? And then
you would raise a question of what would that mean in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. What's the logic of... one way of approaching that
is what's the logic of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. The other thing
to note is that we have now side by side said the
two competing
approaches to רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. The case of the pebbles going
and damaging, that I'm חייב chayav when it goes into your domain
but not when it's in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. In both
cases my freedom... it's the same in terms of my freedom of
movement. So why am I... if I have a right to walk
and when it does the pebbles and it breaks
other vessels in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim I'm פטור, pattur, why all
of a sudden because the pebble went into רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
am I חייב? chayav? And you know, and if you're going to
tell me I'm חייב, chayav, that might stop me from bringing my
animal here, right? So it seems that the only reason there there's
a difference is because in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim you were negligent
because you should have expected this type of damage, whereas... you the
damagee, whereas when it was in רשות הניזק, reshus hanizak, you're not
negligent. So that seems to be the issue of רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim is whether I, the person being damaged, am
negligent or to blame. Whereas this discussion, בכשכשה בזנבה וילך, be-kishkeshah biznavah
ve-yeileich, seems to be more the policy issue that we have to
give you the
freedom to bring your things in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. If that
were true, I'd be פטור pattur even if the pebble went into
your domain because my animal has a right to be in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. Yeah. When an animal gores, do we investigate the
cause of this whether somebody caused that animal to gore?
Yes, that will come up. If something instigated that animal, that's a
different story. Okay, let's just get to the משנה. Anyway this סוגיא
sugya I think was so great. The גמרא does not seem like
it's dealing with what's the reason for רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but
if you just unpack these two side by side cases you have
the two major competing reasons for רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, let's
take a look. בעא רב עינא. Ba'ei Rav Eina. Now this is...
בעי רב עינא. Bey Rav Eina. Now this is going to be
a fun way to end this discussion. קשקשה באמתה מהו? Kishkeshah bi-amatah
ma hu?
If it was wagging its
genitalia, its male member there, what's the הלכה? And it banged over
something. מי אמרינן מידי דהוה אקרן, קרן דאית ליה יצרא תקפה ליה,
הכא נמי לא שנא? Mi amrinan midi de-hava a-keren, keren de-it lei
yetzra takfa leh, hacha nami lo shana? So קרן it's driven by
its יצר הרע. yetzer hara. So here too the יצר yetzer is
fueling this erection here. Okay, הכא נמי לא שנא. Hacha nami lo
shana. Therefore it's חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. reshuth harabbim. או דלמא
קרן כוונתו להזיק הא אין כוונתו להזיק? O dilma keren kavanato lehazik
ha ein kavanato lehazik? Keren is trying to do an intentional act
of damage, this is not. So תיקו. So that, I don't know,
to me the מי אמרינן מידי
דהוה אקרן...
mi amrinan
midi de-hava a-keren... I know. So that like going back to Dov's
question of are we being just formalists here? Like, give me a
break. All along we assumed keren is כוונתו להזיק. kavanato lehazik. What
difference do I care if an animal has a little bit of
a יצר הרע yetzer hara or not? Like why does that change
the nature of the act of damage? And at any rate, it
certainly does not seem to tap into questions of why you're פטור
patur in רשות הרבים. reshuth harabbim. Anyway, this seems to be a
purely category issue. But even as a category issue, why יצרא תקיף
ליה yitzra takif leh would make a difference does not seem clear.
Okay, let's just do the last case. התרנגולים מועדין להלך כדרכן ולשבר.
Ha-tarnagolim muadin le-halech ke-darkan u-leshaber. Okay. אמר רב הונא לא שנו אלא
שנקשר מאליו. Amar Rav Huna lo shanu ela she-nikshar me-elav.
So this was a case that a bucket was tied to the
leg of a chicken and it broke something. Okay, that you pay
half. So he says that's only if it on its own got
tangled up, the bucket, you know, into the leg of the chicken.
אבל קשרו אדם חייב. Aval kasharo adam chayav.
But if a person tied it, the person who tied it is
חייב. chayav. Why? Because we're going to assume
that
the chicken did not damage something through the bucket moving in motion,
the chicken moved the bucket into רשות הרבים reshuth harabbim and somebody
tripped over the bucket. So it's a type of a בור. bor.
So then you're חייב. chayav. Now you might remember going back to
the first פרק perek that one of the cases of a בור
bor that was came from a hybrid of the different categories was
בור המתגלגל ברגלי אדם וברגלי בהמה. bor ha-mitgalgel be-raglei adam u-be-raglei behemah.
That I put something here, an animal kicks it and moves it
somewhere else. If I'm negligent in my original placement and that's then
even if it's moved to another place, it's still my בור. bor.
Okay, so that's what he's saying. If it moved it, it's going
to still be your בור. bor. Now
by
the way, is the owner of the animal חייב chayav if the
animal also participated in bringing this בור bor to רשות הרבים? reshuth
harabbim? And the answer is no, because we're going to see in
a minute, the פסוק pasuk is כי יכרה איש בור, איש בור
ולא שור בור. Ki yichreh ish bor, ish bor ve-lo shor bor.
Only a בור bor dug by a man, not by an animal.
So the owner of the animal is not חייב chayav for the
making of the בור, bor, only the owner of the בור. bor.
So קשרו אדם חייב, kasharo adam chayav,
the person who ties it is חייב. chayav. So נקשר מאליו מאן
חייב? nikshar me-elav man chayav? One minute, if it did it by
itself, who's חייב? chayav? אילימא בעל הדלי, Ilima ba'al ha-deli, the owner
of the bucket. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Now again, we're still assuming
that it's not hitting something, somebody's tripping over it. Okay, so אי
דאצנעי, i de-atzne'ei, if you put your bucket in a
way in a safe place, אנוס הוא, anus hu, you're אנוס. anus.
You protected your bucket, you didn't make a בור, bor, and you're
פטור. patur. ואי לא אצנעי, Ve-i lo atzne'ei, and if you left
it in a place where it could get kicked or tangled by
an animal, פושע הוא, posheia hu, then it is your בור. bor.
אלא חייב בעל התרנגול. Ela chayav ba'al ha-tarnagol.
Okay, so the owner of the תרנגול tarnagol is חייב. chayav. Now
again, we're assuming that somebody tripped over it. One minute. מאי שנא
כולי נזק דלא? Mai shana kulei nezek de-lo? Why
again, we're assuming it's a בור's bor case. So why does the
owner not pay full damages if his chicken made a בור? bor?
דכתיב כי יפתח איש בור ולא שור בור. De-chtiv ki yiftach ish
bor ve-lo shor bor. So if my chicken makes a בור, bor,
I'm פטור. patur. חצי נזק נמי איש בור ולא שור בור. Chatzi
nezek nami ish bor ve-lo shor bor. Okay, so basically if the
case is talking about somebody tripped over it, certainly the owner of
the chicken can't be חייב. chayav. The only possible person to be
חייב chayav is the owner of the bucket if he was negligent,
because that's the idea of a בור. bor. אלא, Ela, you're right.
The משנה is not dealing with the בור bor scenario. משנתינו בדאדי
אדויי. Mishnateinu be-addi aduyei.
The משנה is that the chicken threw it and kicked it and
it broke it in the, you know, through the motion. It's a
type of a צרורות. Okay, that's the
case in the משנה and that's why the owner of the chicken
is חייב chayav because it's צרורות. ואידך דרב הונא בעלמא איתמר. Ve-idach
de-Rav Huna be-alma itmar. And this statement of רב הונא Rav Huna
which conceives of a case like this about a בור, bor, that's
not on the משנה, but in general. דלי הפקר. Deli hefker. You
have a bucket that's ownerless. אמר רב הונא נקשר מאליו פטור. Amar
Rav Huna nikshar me-elav patur. If it on its own got tied
up by a chicken, you're exempt. קשרו אדם חייב. Kasharo adam chayav.
But if a person tied it up, then he's פושע posheia and
he made a בור. bor. So the גמרא says, מאי שנא... Mai
shana... Right. So meaning that רב הונא's Rav Huna case is a
בור bor case. The משנה case is a כוחו case. רב הונא's
Rav Huna case is a בור bor case. So you've got a
בור. bor. The chicken, owner of the chicken is going to be
פטור patur because of איש בור ולא שור בור. ish bor ve-lo
shor bor. Is the owner of the bucket going to be חייב?
chayav? Well, if you consciously tied it up to the chicken, you're
going to be חייב. chayav. So the גמרא says, משום מאי חייב?
Mishum mai chayav? Or if you were negligent, you don't have to
literally tie it to the chicken. But if you were negligent with
your bucket, you'd be חייב. chayav. משום מאי חייב? Mishum mai chayav?
אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משום בור המתגלגל ברגלי אדם וברגלי בהמה,
Amar Rav Huna bar Manoach mishum bor ha-mitgalgel be-raglei adam u-be-raglei behemah,
because you made a בור bor that got moved by an animal.
by a person or an animal, but if you're negligent with the
bucket and then somebody trips over it, even if they tripped over
it in another place, because your negligence led to it being moved
by an animal to another place, you're still חייב. chayav. So again,
you cannot be חייב chayav if your animal makes a בור. bor.
You can be חייב chayav if you put something down and you're
negligent and can anticipate it's going to get moved, or you put
it down in רשות הרבים reshus harabim and it gets moved to
another place, then that is your בור. bor. The one interesting question
which I'll leave with, which תוספות Tosafos raised on רש"י is, let's
say it's the case that it's the animal's כח, koach, but I
was negligent with my bucket. I left my bucket in רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, or let's say רשות הי... reshus hay... wherever it is,
let's not worry about רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. I left my bucket
in a place where I knew it could get kicked by an
animal and get damaged and somebody could damage, and the animal kicked
it and damaged. So the owner of the animal pays half because
of צרורות. Do I pay? What would I be paying for? What
type of a category would you put that in? My bucket got
kicked by an animal and I knew that could have happened and
it did damage. What type of a category is that?
It's not שור, shor, it's not בור, bor, right? What is it?
אדם? Adam? No, so the question is, is it
אש? esh? You put something in a place where some other power
can move it and cause it to create damage. Is that like
a case of a fire? So תוספות Tosafos says that would be
אש. esh. So the owner of the chicken would pay half because
of צרורות, and I'd probably pay the other half because of אש.
esh. Anyway, that's the case that the גמרא did not fully explore.
All right, we'll end with this.